BU Records: Dean of Women (Lily Russell), Inclusive: 1922-1969, undated, Bulk: 1935-1945
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Dean of Women (Lily Russell)
Inclusive: 1922-1969, undated, Bulk: 1935-1945
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/372
Russell, Lily McIlroy, 1887 - 1958
19 document boxes and 1 oversized box.
BU Records: Dean of Women (Lily Russell) includes records created and collected by Lily Russell during her tenure as Assistant Dean of Women and Dean of Women at Baylor University.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Lily McIlroy Russell was born in Kerrville, Texas, on 1887 January 24. Her father, Rev. Chester A. McIlroy, moved the family to New Mexico after the death of his spouse. While in New Mexico, the family met the Claypool family. When Chester McIlroy accepted a position in Oklahoma, the Claypools took in the McIlroy children. After accepting positions at Baylor University, the blended family moved to Waco, Texas. Eventually, Russell attended Baylor and graduated in 1911.
After graduation, she taught English at Baylor and, in 1917, was married. Although she later divorced her husband (date unknown), she retained the last name Russell. In 1924, she moved to Portland, Oregon, and later returned to Baylor in 1926 to accept the position of assistant to Irene Marschall, Dean of Women. When Marschall left the university in 1931, Russell was offered the position, which she would occupy for the next nine years.
As Dean of Women, Russell was involved in multiple aspects of female student life at Baylor. She was a member of the Woman’s Missionary Union and coordinated some of the organization’s outreach efforts at Baylor such as the Margaret Fund and special events. Special events included District Meetings and "houseparties," multiple day affairs for area members of the Young Women’s Auxiliary and Girl’s Auxiliary. Russell was a major participant in event and entertainment planning at Baylor, an area she remained engaged in throughout her tenure.
In 1940, Baylor President Pat M. Neff named Russell the Director of Public Relations and chairperson of the Baylor Centennial Committee. After Baylor’s Centennial celebration in 1945, she continued as Public Relations director until accepting the position of Dean of the Union Building in 1948. Due to her vast knowledge and collection of information about Baylor’s history, Russell accepted her last position as Baylor’s official University Historian in 1950.
Russell was a well-known person on the Baylor campus, and the students dedicated the 1955 edition of the Baylor annual, The Round-Up, to her. During the 1950s, she began to write a complete history of Baylor from its beginnings in Independence, Texas. However, Russell would not be able to complete the project. In 1958, she became ill and began working from home with the assistance of two student secretaries. Later that year, on 1958 August 21, Lily Russell passed away.
Scope and Content
BU Records: Dean of Women (Lily Russell) is organized according to Lily Russell’s time as Assistant Dean of Women (beginning in 1926) and Dean of Women (beginning in 1931). Materials are predominantly related to administrative functions and event planning. A large amount of correspondence is included and full dialogues are present as Russell would copy her initial solicitations and responses. Original letters and postcards are typically attached to copied responses in the reverse order in which they were received. Many newspaper clippings were present and attached to discarded letters, drafts of material, and ballots from past events. Although the clippings were the intended items to be retained, the items to which they are attached to provide context and additional information not found elsewhere in the collection. Other sizeable amounts of materials present in the collection include photographs and event materials (programs, scripts, sheet music, decorative items, etc.). A large percentage of items in the collection contain handwritten notes by Russell. Depending upon the item, the notes could be as simple as a label or as complex as detailed instructions.
Russell continued to use many of the files in her various other roles at the university, so many extend past her tenure as Dean of Women. It is unclear whether student assistants used the files while Russell worked from home in her later years. Material originating from successors may also be found within some series. Additional materials were included after her death, and it is possible files may have been used and altered by others before storage and transfer to The Texas Collection.
Arrangement
BU Records: Dean of Women (Lily Russell) had been organized prior to this finding aid, but with no inventory of the entire collection or existing finding aid. It was not clear if this arrangement was in the original order or imposed by an archivist upon accession. Arrangement and titles were derived from the existing materials. In order to enhance access, minor alterations were made and those changes are noted in the finding aid.
Currently, BU Records: Dean of Women (Lily Russell) is in 14 series: I. Margaret Fund Students, II. Baptist Denomination, III. Women’s Files, IV. Accounting Department Correspondence, V. Special Convocations, VI. Fellowship Girls, VII. Field Day, VIII. Dormitory Handbooks and Pamphlets, IX. Programming, X. Photographs, XI. Datebooks, XII. Forms, XIII. Dormitories, XIV: Literary Productions. Series X. Photographs is further arranged in five subseries: Student Individuals, Student Individuals Annual, Tennis (Sports), Student Individuals (Studio), Student Pictures. Series XIII. Dormitories is further arranged into two subseries: Management and Catherine Alexander Dormitory.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/372. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Items in related collections
BU Records: Dean of the Union Building (Lily Russell), Inclusive: 1936-1966, Bulk: 1946-1954
Lily McIlroy Russell papers, Inclusive: 1897-1968; Bulk: 1942-1958
BU Records: Historical Research Office, Inclusive: 1863-1974, undated, Bulk: 1944-1960, undated
Related references
“500 Girls Expected at Y.W.A. House Party.” The Summer Lariat (Waco, TX), 1939 August 15. Accessed 2013 September 5.
Baylor University. The Round-Up. Waco, Texas: 1939. Accessed 2013 September 5.
Baylor University. The Round-Up. Waco, Texas: 1940. Accessed 2013 September 5.
Baylor University. The Round-Up. Waco, Texas: 1941. Accessed 2013 September 5.
Baylor University. The Round-Up.Waco, Texas: 1942. Accessed 2013 September 5.
Baylor University. The Round-Up. Waco, Texas: 1955. Accessed 2013 September 5.
Cook, Zandra. "The Margaret Fund: A Story of Persistence and Support at Baylor University in the 1930s." HESA Baylor History Project. Accessed 2020 May 6.
“Garners Receive Baylor Degrees.” The Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), Nov. 24, 1936. Accessed 2013 September 5.
“W.M.U. Sponsors Event for Central Texas Students.” The Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1935 April 5. Accessed 2013 September 5.
Wallace, Patricia Ward. A Spirit So Rare: A History Of The Women Of Waco. Austin: Nortex Press, 1984.
“The What, When, Why, Who, Where and How of the Margaret Fund.” Birmingham: Woman’s Missionary Union, S. B. C., n.d.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Russell, Lily McIlroy, 1887-.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History -- 20th century.; Southern Baptist Convention.
Subjects
Baptist associations -- United States.; Baptists -- Texas -- History.; Baptists -- Texas -- Waco.; Baylor University -- Events.; Baylor University -- Faculty.; Dormitories -- Texas -- Waco.; Education, Higher -- Texas -- History.; Women -- Education (Higher) -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Handbooks and manuals.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Programs.; Radio scripts.; Reports.
- Margaret Fund Students, 1933-1955, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series consists chiefly of correspondence regarding recipients of the Margaret Fund. The Margaret Fund was a scholarship administered through the Woman’s Missionary Union for children of foreign missionaries. Russell was an active participant in the Woman’s Missionary Union and an intermediary between donors and Margaret Fund students. The series contains detailed information about fund recipients, lists of eligible students, lists of missionaries, lists of foreign students, Baptist publications, and some photographs.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Margaret Fund Students 1933-1935, 1933-1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1936, 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1938-1939 (1 of 3), 1936-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1938-1939 (2 of 3), 1936-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1938-1939 (3 of 3), 1936-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1939-1940 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1939-1940 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1942-1944, 1946-1947 (1 of 2), 1941-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1942-1944, 1946-1947 (2 of 2), 1941-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1948-1949, 1948-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1950-1952, 1951-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Margaret Fund Students 1955, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Baptist Denomination, 1931-1969, undated; 2
  This series chronicles Baylor University’s involvement and perception within the Baptist denomination and related organizations. The series spans from Lily Russell’s role as Acting Dean of Women in 1931 through her remaining years at Baylor in various roles.
  Baylor and Russell’s involvement with the Woman’s Missionary Union and the Southern Baptist Convention is represented within the series. Materials related to specific annual meetings of the Southern Baptist Convention are present. Also included is documentation regarding “Houseparties” that were multiple day affairs for area members of the Young Women’s Auxiliary and Girl’s Auxiliary. Members of those organizations were invited to Baylor for a multiple day program that included classes, guest speakers, and other events. Other topics within the series include a Texas Baptist Training Union Convention and Baptist publications.
  The series includes newspaper clippings, article drafts, correspondence, event programs, photographs, invitations, reports, schedules, radio scripts, and notes. Event related materials typically include planning materials, correspondence with attendees, and items from events.
  - Baptist General Convention (1 of 3), 1931-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Baptist General Convention (2 of 3), 1931-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Baptist General Convention (3 of 3), 1931-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Baptist General Convention of Texas (1 of 4), 1940-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Baptist General Convention of Texas (2 of 4), 1940-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Baptist General Convention of Texas (3 of 4), 1940-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Baptist General Convention of Texas (4 of 4), 1940-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Baptist Standard, 1943-1945, 1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Baptist World Alliance, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Baylor and the Baptist (1 of 3), 1944-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Baylor and the Baptist (2 of 3), 1944-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Baylor and the Baptist (3 of 3), 1944-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Baylor and the Denomination, 1945-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Baylor and Evangelism, 1955-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Baylor and the W.M.U. (Woman’s Missionary Union) (1 of 2), 1944-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Baylor and the W.M.U. (Woman’s Missionary Union) (2 of 2), 1944-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Dr. B.Q. Program, 1948-1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - North American Baptists, 1955-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Southern Baptist Convention - General, 1934, 1940-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Southern Baptist Convention 1942-1943, 1941-1943, 1955-1956, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Southern Baptist Convention 1946, 1946, 1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Southern Baptist Convention 1955, 1941-1943, 1955-1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Southern Baptist Convention 1957, 1948, 1956-1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Training Union of Texas, 1947, 1951-1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Y.W.A. (Young Women’s Auxiliary) — G.A. (Girl’s Auxiliary) Houseparty 1937-1942 (1 of 2), 1936-1948, 1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Y.W.A. (Young Women’s Auxiliary) — G.A. (Girl’s Auxiliary) Houseparty 1937-1942 (2 of 2), 1936-1948, 1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Y.W.A. (Young Women’s Auxiliary) — G.A. (Girl’s Auxiliary) Houseparty 1947-1948, 1947-1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Y.W.A. (Young Women’s Auxiliary) — G.A. (Girl’s Auxiliary) Houseparty 1950’s, 1950-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Women’s Files, 1937-1944, 1953-1957, undated; 3
  This series contains Lily Russell’s research on the history of women in higher education and current events of the day that featured women. The series is chiefly correspondence with various educational and government institutions in addition to newspaper clippings highlighting women or women’s groups in newspaper articles. The bulk of the newspaper articles are related to the role of women in society, with an emphasis on Baylor connections. Also included are various publications and advertisements for publications regarding the status of women in education and society.
  - Education of Women, 1939-1941, 1955, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Women — General, 1937-1944, 1953-1957, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Accounting Department Correspondence, 1938-1942, undated; 4
  Originally a single folder titled “Accounting Department**Truett Grant, Cashier” this series contains correspondence between Lily Russell and Truett Grant (Baylor University’s cashier) regarding finances. Correspondence includes authorization for expenses, dormitory billing, student accounts, etc. Also included is an index of correspondence and notes about expenses and reimbursement.
  - Correspondence and Index, 1940-1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (1 of 3), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (2 of 3), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (3 of 3), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and Notes, 1938, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Special Convocations, 1936, 1954, undated; 5
  This series contains materials related to a convocation that presented the then current United States Vice President, John Nance Gardner, and his wife, Mariette "Ettie" Rheiner Garner, with honorary degrees from Baylor University. Items include event planning materials, photographs of the event, article drafts, newspapers, the event program, and an event ticket.
  - Garner Convocation (1 of 2), 1936, 1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Garner Convocation (2 of 2), 1936, 1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Fellowship Girls, 1936-1940, undated; 6
  Originally a folder titled simply “Fellowship”, this series consists of material predominantly related to a group of female students receiving assistance that Lily Russell referred to as “Fellowship Girls.” This series is similar to that of the Margaret Fund Students series and contains some materials regarding Margaret Fund students. The bulk of the series consists of lists of students and correspondence about their status.
  - Fellowship, 1936-1940, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Field Day, 1933-1942, undated; 7
  General condition: Poor.
  Field Day was a program sponsored by the Woman’s Missionary Union for high school seniors within the surrounding counties. Also known as the “District Meet” or “At Home,” the event invited students to spend the day at Baylor University. Attendees would be greeted with a reception, taken on guided tours of campus by Baylor students, allowed to visit various university departments, and given tickets to events. Lily Russell assisted in coordinating the event and communicated with educators and student tour guides. Materials include correspondence, lists of high school seniors from surrounding counties (some with contact information), attendance information, lists of student tour guides, Baylor class schedules, directions for tour guides, personal notes, and event tickets. The folders containing “Field Day 1938” materials also contained materials for all previous years of the event (1933-1937).
  - Field Day 1933, 1933-1936, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Field Day 1934, 1933-1934, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Field Day 1935 (1 of 2), 1934-1936, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Field Day 1935 (2 of 2), 1934-1936, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Field Day 1936 (1 of 2), 1935-1936, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Field Day 1936 (2 of 2), 1935-1936, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Field Day, 1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Field Day 1937-1938 (1 of 3), 1937-1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Field Day 1937-1938 (2 of 3), 1937-1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Field Day 1937-1938 (3 of 3), 1937-1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Field Day 1938 (1 of 5), 1933-1941, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Field Day 1938 (2 of 5), 1933-1941, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Field Day 1938 (3 of 5), 1933-1941, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Field Day 1938 (4 of 5), 1933-1941, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Field Day 1938 (5 of 5), 1933-1941, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Field Day 1939 (1 of 4), 1938-1939, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Field Day 1939 (2 of 4), 1938-1939, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Field Day 1939 (3 of 4), 1938-1939, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Field Day 1939 (4 of 4), 1938-1939, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Dormitory Handbooks and Pamphlets, 1938-1963, undated; 8
  General condition: Good.
  This series consists of books and pamphlets related to dormitories that were found within the Field Day materials. The pamphlets are most likely those given to incoming female occupants to Baylor’s dormitories. They outline the rules of the dormitory and describe issues related to life on campus. Handbooks are related to managing students and administrative functions of residence halls.
  - Dormitory Pamphlets, 1938-1939, 1959-1963, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Dormitory Management Handbooks, 1947, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Programming, 1922-1957, undated; 9
  Originally titled "Programs", this series contains materials Lily Russell used in presenting events and productions. Upon Russell’s return to Baylor in 1926, she became involved in campus entertainment. Russell organized theatrical productions which often included original compositions. The series includes song lyrics, original sheet music, scripts (often with notes or alterations), costume patterns, presentation notes, correspondence, invitations, drafts of event programs, actual event programs, photographs, advertisements for guest speakers and entertainers, decorative items, and items used as inspiration or reference. A folder titled “Programs” was renamed “Program Materials” and contains event programs, event planning materials, and notes about productions. The series is largely undated and productions could have had repeated performances. Somewhat related materials found within the series are a number of greeting cards sent to Russell and a 1955 datebook which has been isolated in a separate folder.
  - Alice in Baylorland, 1931, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Christmas Dances, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Christmas Music, 1940-1941, undated (Box 20 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Christmas Programs, 1929-1956, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Cowboy Songs, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Feb. (February) — George Washington Programs, 1931-1932, 1957, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Halloween, 1937, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Latin Banquet, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Matrimony — Seven Ages, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Mother’s Day, 1936, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - “Old Christmas” Program (1 of 2), undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - “Old Christmas” Program (2 of 2), undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Outside Entertainments, 1937-1939, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Party Suggestions (1 of 7), 1928-1936, 1954-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Party Suggestions [Datebook, 1955] (2 of 7), 1928-1936, 1954-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Party Suggestions (3 of 7), 1928-1936, 1954-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Party Suggestions (4 of 7), 1928-1936, 1954-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Party Suggestions (5 of 7), 1928-1936, 1954-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Party Suggestions (6 of 7), 1928-1936, 1954-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Party Suggestions (7 of 7), 1928-1936, 1954-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Parties — General (1 of 3), 1922-1927, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Parties — General (2 of 3), 1922-1927, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Parties — General (2 of 3), 1922-1927, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Patriotic Parties, 1934, 1956, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Plays-Talks-Readings, 1924, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Poetry — Personal, 1940, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Program Materials (1 of 3), 1929, 1935-1944, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Program Materials (2 of 3), 1929, 1935-1944, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Program Materials (3 of 3), 1929, 1935-1944, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Religious Programs, 1930-1937, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - St. Patrick’s Day, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Texas Programs, 1933, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Thanksgiving Parties (1 of 2), 1927-1938, 1955, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Thanksgiving Parties (1 of 2), 1927-1938, 1955, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Valentine and Easter Parties, 1926, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Decorative Items, 1930, undated (Box 20 OVZ, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1939-1942, undated; 10
  This series is comprised of album pages used to create Baylor University’s annual, The Round-Up, from the late 1930s and early 1940s (please see attached images for examples). Most photographs are small portraits that were trimmed and pasted onto sheets of paper to create an aesthetic arrangement. To preserve materials and enhance access, photographs pasted onto deteriorating paper were removed. Pages of photographs that could be grouped together, but did not have any other information about the arrangement, are labeled "Annual Pages." "Uncut portraits" are portraits that were not trimmed or pasted into arrangements. Many include an identification card that provides information about the individual. In addition to portraits, some photographs depict student life and are identified as simply "photographs." In rare instances, alternate selections are included throughout the series. Some photographs are damaged, but the series is in overall average condition.
  - Student Individuals, undated; 1